<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text author="Drago Jančar" title="Northern Lights" translator="Michael Biggins" year="2001"
  place="Evanston (Ill.)" publisher="Northwestern University Press">
  <chapter n="1">

    <p xml:id="p1">
      <seg xml:id="s1">Outside the railway station Erdman caught sight of the gloomy facade of some
        building.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s2">High up above, two windows were lit.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s3">For an instant it seemed as if the huddled city's eyes were watching him.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s4">He walked down the empty street through wet, snowy slush.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s5">When he turned the corner past the house with the shining eyes, there was a
        human shape wavering in the darkness.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s6">The street had been deserted, making the appearance of this phantom before
        him unexpected.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s7">It had to have come out of an entryway, or from behind some pillar, if it
        hadn't just sprouted up from the ground.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s8">Behind it were the dark facades of old buildings and in the early morning
        darkness it was scarcely even possible at first to make out the figure.</seg>
    </p>

    <p xml:id="p2">
      <seg xml:id="s9">"<hi rend="italic">Khristos voskrese</hi>," the man shouted.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s10">"<hi rend="italic">Voistinu voskrese.</hi>"</seg>
    </p>

    <p xml:id="p3">
      <seg xml:id="s11">He swayed and bent at the waist, and his whirling arms jabbed strange shapes
        in the air.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s12">For an instant Erdman may have been frightened of this bearded man in ragged
        clothes; he may not have been quite sure what the words meant, what the point was of this
        bending and arm waving.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s13">To be sure, at first he couldn't decide whether the man in front of him was
        drunk or dangerous or just slightly stupid.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s14">He tried to sidestep him, but with a sudden leap that no one would have
        thought his twisted shape capable of, the other blocked his way.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s15">Erdman had the rumble of the train in his ears, the glare of deserted
        stations in his eyes, and here he was accosted by the empty silence of this street, a dark
        morning with the dilapidated facades of unknown buildings and then, suddenly, this contorted
        face and wobbly human form that refused to let him pass.</seg>
    </p>

    <p xml:id="p4">
      <seg xml:id="s16">He set his suitcase down on the dirty, slushy mess of snow and human
        footprints.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s17">He heard only silence and waited for a human voice to speak to him again out
        of the red cavity of a mouth before him.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s18">Erdman was tired and for a second he felt as though the street were sliding
        out from under his legs.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s19">He ascribed the strange sensation to the long train trip, yet he still
        propped himself up with a hand against the wall.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s20">The other bent at the waist again and stretched his neck out, turning his
        face upward.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s21">Then he straightened and stepped up to him.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s22">Erdman could feel the other's warm breath on his face, and he really felt
        like going.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s23">He would turn around and go.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s24">He didn't turn around.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s25">He didn't pick up his suitcase, and he didn't push the phantom out of the
        way.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s26">Because at that moment, he noticed the other's tiny pupils, which were
        completely at peace.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s27">Completely at peace in that bearded, distorted face, in that body nervously
        jerking back and forth.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s28">Erdman couldn't stop staring at the other's eyes, which were hollow and
        deep, as though they were the precipice leading into a chasm, as if they concealed a
        bottomless darkness.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s29">He stood there and stared at those eyes and at that face that was furrowed
        by something inside it, and he could see that these were in fact very quiet, very still
        eyes.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s30">These weren't the eyes of a drunk or an idiot.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s31">These were eyes that were afraid of something.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s32">Not just anything, but something that was simply, surely going to happen and
        that could not be avoided.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s33">These were Fedyatin's eyes.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s34">This was exactly how it had to be. Fedyatin's face and his quiet eyes, his
        tiny black pupils, and the deep, dark abyss behind them were what he had to see on this
        morning, with dilapidated buildings in the background, the slushy street, a morning that was
        quiet from earth to heaven.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s35">And Erdman had to start when he saw the dark red stains on the other's coat,
        when he concluded that those spots were from some blood or other.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s36">The street slid slightly from under his feet again, and he held tighter onto
        the wall.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s37">He may have thought then that he should just turn around and go back where
        he came from.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s38">He didn't turn around and he didn't go back.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s39">Who in this world has left a city where he wanted to find out something,
        based on some vague intuition? Who has ever held back on account of any intuition at all?</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s40">Intuition exists to propel you even more decisively toward the inevitable.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s41">And so that early-morning phantom with the black pupils and dark red stains
        on its coat was nothing but a drunken, rumpled man with a slightly idiotic face.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s42">And so Erdman stayed and he remained standing there in the street even after
        Fedyatin had already disappeared among the dark facades of the buildings, still swaying
        incessantly, after he vanished into the facades, the morning herald and agitator of the
        resurrection.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s43">Erdman stood alone beside a wall on Alexander Street, overwhelmed by the
        powerful, throbbing silence of that morning, a shuddering silence that hovered over Central
        Europe, echoed off the walls of streets in Prague, and soundlessly beat and gnawed the
        shores of Duino.</seg>
      <seg xml:id="s44">He looked over toward the Franciscan church and waited for a bell up above
        to ring.</seg>
    </p>

    <p xml:id="p5">
      <seg xml:id="s45">That was early on the morning of the first of January 1938.</seg>
    </p>

    <note type="footnote" target="#p2">
      <seg xml:id="s46"><hi rend="italic">Khristos voskrese. ... Voistinu voskrese.</hi> "Christ is
        risen. ... He is risen indeed." <hi rend="italic">Voskrese</hi> (Church Slavic) and <hi
          rend="italic">voskres</hi> (Russian), a variant found in chapters 58 and 80, are used
        interchangeably.</seg>
    </note>

  </chapter>
</text>